<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abstracts of some letters written by Mr. Robert Rich treating mostly of spiritual matters and here transmitted to posterity and recommended to the sober and serious enquirer for promoting of universal love amongst all sorts of people without respect of persons, parties, or sects : together with a friendly letter of Dr. Jer. Taylor to the said R.R. in answer to one of his / published by J.P.</title>
            <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09459438</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09459438</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43178</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43178)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1314:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abstracts of some letters written by Mr. Robert Rich treating mostly of spiritual matters and here transmitted to posterity and recommended to the sober and serious enquirer for promoting of universal love amongst all sorts of people without respect of persons, parties, or sects : together with a friendly letter of Dr. Jer. Taylor to the said R.R. in answer to one of his / published by J.P.</title>
                  <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
                  <author>Pennyman, John, 1628-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Billingsley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43178:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ABSTRACTS OF SOME LETTERS WRITTEN BY Mr. <hi>ROBERT RICH,</hi> Treating moſtly of Spiritual Matters, Are here tranſmitted to Poſterity, and recommended to the ſober and ſerious Enquirer, FOR Promoting of Univerſal Love amongſt all ſorts of People, without reſpect of Perſons, Parties, or Sects.</p>
            <p>Together with a friendly Letter of Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor,</hi> to the ſaid <hi>R. R.</hi> in Anſwer to one of his.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by a Lover of RIGHTEOUSNES But an utter Enemy to Deceit and Wickedneſs in whomſoever J. P.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Billingſley,</hi> at the Printing-Preſs, near the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>al-Exchange, in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:43178:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43178:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Having had the peruſal of divers of <hi>Mr. R. Rich's</hi> Letters, (by reaſon of his late Deceaſe) found ſeveral things (ſcattered up and down amongſt them) of a ſublime and Divine Nature, ſome of which I picked and culled out, and now expoſe to publick view, chiefly for the ſake of thoſe whoſe Hearts and Minds are ſet <hi>Sion</hi>-wards, to be kept upon Record for their Poſterity, even the Generations of all the juſt and righteous Ones, of what Nation, Kindred, Tongue, or People ſoever they be. For the ſincere, ſingle, and upright-hearted, in whom there is no Guile, (who ſeek not the Praiſe of Men, but the Glory of the Lord only) were, are, and for ever will be acted and guided by one and the ſame Spirit [of Purity, Holineſs, and Self-denial] through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Ages and Generations. <hi>He that can receive the Teſtimony of this Truth,</hi> (as did the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> of old, and as do the Servants of the Lord now) <hi>let him;</hi> but withal let him know, unleſs his Life and Converſation be harmleſs and blameleſs amongſt Men, all his <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Truth in words</hi> will but add to his greater Condemnation: For <hi>he that talks of his Maſter's Will, and is not a doer of the ſame, muſt expect to be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> Wherefore my Advice is, before any talk of, or intermeddle with the Secrets or Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Great GOD, they firſt ſee <hi>Juſtice, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and Love to <hi>Equity,</hi> ſet up in their own Souls; for till that be reſolvedly and fixedly eſtabliſhed within, all Knowledg and Profeſſion without will avail little: <hi>For what doth the Lord require of thee, O Man, but to do juſtly, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly before Him?</hi> Therefore let theſe things, in which the Kingdom of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſists, (and not in Meats or Drinks, Habits, Times, or Places, which at beſt were but ſhadows of good things to come,) be first ſought after, and all other things needful will be added; as hath been fully and truly experienced by one who hath learned, not only to <hi>forgive Enemies,</hi> but can, with delight, <hi>reward Evil with Good.</hi> Which Leſſon, that the Reader may learn, preſs after, and attain unto, is the deſire of him, who ſeeks the Good and Weal of all Mankind.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43178:3"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Rich</hi>'s Letter to Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi> of the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>Feb. 1657.</hi> Together with the Doctor's Anſwer.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing in my Heart perſuaded, that there are many of late years which have ſuffered much in their Perſons, Eſtates, and good Names, of thoſe People called <hi>Malignants,</hi> eſpecially ſome that were in the Miniſtry, that were not only put out of their Livings, but by an Act made uncapable of that Emploiment their Education beſt fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for, <hi>viz.</hi> the keeping of Schools. And altho perhaps ſome might ſuffer juſtly for their Offences, yet I do believe many of them did ſuffer for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, not daring to make ſhipwrack of it, nor to act againſt that Light or Knowledg, which to them was made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt from the Lord to be juſt and right. Towards ſuch have I great Love, notwithſtanding the different Diſpenſations, Manifeſtations, Operations, and Adminiſtrations wherein we are caſt, knowing the Root and Ground to be from the one Spirit, and that in my Father's Houſe there are many Manſions, in which as every one abides to act and do the things that are juſt and right, they are accepted with him, of what Nation, Kindred, or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoever, whether <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> they are all one in Chriſt Jeſus, God's Talent and Gift to the World, who doth enlighten every one freely by his Grace both to will and to do, of his good pleaſure. And therefore as a Teſtimony of that Love the Lord hath begot in my Heart to all Men, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to them that improve my Lord's Talent, and who are of his Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and abide in the Faith (that keeps clean the Heart) which is held in a pure Conſcience, have I by this Bearer ſent unto you Ten Pounds to beſtow amongſt them you know to be in want, under that Form called <hi>Epiſcopal.</hi> And this I feel to be well-pleaſing to God, (and hath a Reward from him,) altho it ſhould be condemned by Man. So deſiring you in this thing to act, as Truth in the inward parts ſhall direct, I commit you to the Grace and Love of God; where I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant, <hi>R. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43178:3"/>
            <head>The Doctor's Anſwer.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received from you (by the hands of your Nephew) a Letter, and Ten Pounds, to be given to ſuch godly Miniſters of the Epiſcopal Perſuaſion, who are in want, and ſuffer for the Teſtimony of their Conſciences. <hi>Sir,</hi> I do in their behalf return my humble thanks to God, who hath put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Heart to do ſo good, ſo charitable an Action, for the relief of his afflicted Servants. And I return hearty thanks to You alſo, and do very much rejoice in that Piety and godly Sincerity of your Spirit, by which you endeavour, by your Love unto the Brethren, to teſtify your Love and Duty to our deareſt Lord. I ſee you are no reſpecter of Perſons, nor Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but that you enquire after the Power of Godlineſs; and I am very much delighted to conſider, that you make a charitable Judgment of your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who are under another Diſpenſation. As long as the Underſtandings of Men differ, there will be variety of Judgments; but the Work of God, and of Religion, goes forward, while we have but one Heart, and one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Sir, I hope you will have great cauſe to rejoice, when you ſhall hear that God is glorified on your behalf, and that you by your liberal Alms cauſe humble Thankſgivings to be made to God. For my own particular, I ſhall by God's aſſiſtance do the Office of a faithful Steward, in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of your Liberality; and I pray God to accept it at your hands, and to reward it ſevenfold into your Boſom. Sir, I humbly take my leave, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very affectionate Friend and Servant in the Lord Jeſus, <hi>JER, TAYLOR.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> 13. 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>This following is a Preamble of a Letter, <hi>R. R.</hi> writ to the Earl of <hi>Windſor.</hi> Jan. <hi>10. 1662.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr ſome time I ſcrupled, and durſt call no Man Lord or Maſter, which proceeded from Tradition received from Elders, &amp; from the Letter of the Scripture, which ſaith, <hi>Call no Man Maſter.</hi> But having ſince that in my ſelf felt a more ſure Word, <hi>viz.</hi> the Image or Talent of God, (to wit) Truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, by and through which I ſee and know how to give to God thoſe things which belong to him, and unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> likewiſe his due. For as with my Soul I own God only to be my Lord and Teacher, ſo over my outward Humanity (for divers reſpects) I can as truly call Man my Lord and Maſter alſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43178:4"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of a Letter <hi>R. R.</hi> wrote to an endeared Friend of his, called a <hi>Quaker, 1657.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Heart,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOw is it that I hear in thee a Voice of weeping, <hi>Rachel</hi> mourning for her Children? Wotteſt thou not that I muſt go about my Father's buſineſs? and that for this end I came into the World, to bear witneſs to the Truth? Was not my ſelf, and many more innocent ones caſt out from amongſt them, and ſold into <hi>Egypt?</hi> Many dark things laid to our charge, which we never ſaid nor did? I would not have thee one with them in their Work, to fight their Battels, either to juſtify the wicked, or condemn the innocent, leſt thou partake with them in their Judgments, (as <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> did in ſiding and making a Confederacy with <hi>Ahab</hi>) who daily impoſe upon their Brethren, and will not let them go free, to act what the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of them. O <hi>Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem!</hi> how oft have I ſought to find Love in thee towards thy Brethren? and when it fled, how oft have I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued after it?</p>
            <p>I believe I might have been received again into fellowſhip amongſt them, but then I muſt firſt have turned the Truth of God into a Lie, and ſpoke evil of thoſe things I knew to be good, denying the Teſtimony which I knew the Lord gave me to finiſh, and ſo have betrayed Jeſus: which thing I ſhall never do, ſo long as the Breath of the Almighty is in me, nor call any Man Maſter of my Light and Spirit, ſave God only. And if now at length the Lord hath ſeen the Oppreſſion of his People, and is coming to plead their Cauſe, or hath raiſed up any to be a Rod or Scourge, to whip out of his Temple thoſe that have bought or ſold the Innocent for a thing of nought; what am I, that I ſhould reſiſt, or judg evil of them that do his Will? Or if any be commanded of the Lord to feaſt <hi>Haman,</hi> why ſhould <hi>Mordecai</hi> be offended thereat? For my part, I have long ſeen where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Liberty and Freedom of the Son conſiſteth, and that this is he that loves his Enemy, that rewards evil with good, and doth not ſalute a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only; this is He that is Heir of all things, and muſt reign, tho at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Face be more marred than any Man's; and bleſſed is he that is not offended in Him, but is made conformable in all things to Him, he muſt reign alſo. But he that judges his Brother in Meats or Drinks, or any other outward thing, that contends more for his own Traditions, than the Commands of God, that will not let his Brother go free to worſhip God where and how he requireth, I ſay, this is the Son of the Bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which muſt be caſt out, and ſhall not inherit. I am not troubled to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43178:4"/>ſee the Lord coming to plead the Cauſe of the Innocent, and to make a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration betwixt the two Seeds, who have ſerved the Lord, and who have ſerved their own ends; and bleſſed are they who with joy can ſtand the Trial.</p>
            <p>O dear Heart, enter thou not into their Secrets, nor ſay a Confederacy with blood-thirſty Men, who have uſurped Authority over the meaſure of God in their Brethren, and with <hi>Herod</hi> have ſlain the <hi>Man-child</hi> begot in many, and would not hear his Teſtimony, nor ſuffer his Voice to be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As the Lord lives, their Nakedneſs ſhall be no longer hid, and what hath long lain ſecret, muſt now be preached upon the Houſe-top, and herein the Innocent can and will rejoice.</p>
            <p>I am Bone of their Bone, and Fleſh of their Fleſh, who are innocent, and of an upright Heart with the Lord in what is made manifeſt; ſuch a one is as my Father and Mother, Siſter and Brother.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another to the ſame Perſon, <hi>1658.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O That thou wert not one with them that have condemned their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Brethren in Meats and Drink, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all which are but ſhadows of good things, and muſt periſh; but the Body is Chriſt. For my part, my Hat to me is no more than any other part of my Apparel; and I find I may without ſin ſhew the Love I have in my Heart to any by putting off my Hat, and that it is to me all one as if I gave my hand, and ſignifies the ſame thing: Yet I would not have all others to follow me in this, but firſt to examine themſelves, and ſo let them eat and drink, left they eat and drink their own damnation. Neither dare I judg any, that can love his Enemy, or do good to the good and to the bad, or that can become all things (that is not evil in the ſight of God) to all Men, to ſave all; I am perſuaded ſuch do well to follow the Lord, when he leads into theſe things. I dare not judge ſuch to be Men-pleaſers, or to be one with the wicked in their evil, but rather judg ſuch an one to be an Example to all the Children of God, as being moſt like our heavenly Father. For my part I have great reward with the Lord, for bearing my Teſtimony againſt this Spirit of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, which hath been as high as Heaven, but my hope is, the Lord will bring it down as low as Hell, and in this Faith have I reſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43178:5"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of a Letter written by <hi>R. R.</hi> to <hi>R. M.</hi> a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONe of you being offended at my ſpeaking a few words in your Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſaid, <hi>He knew my Spirit to be in oppoſition:</hi> T o whom I replied, If it be ſo framed, ought not I to be faithful to what it requires? Certainly the Majeſty of true Love and Meekneſs would have born what I had to offer, and not have been offended; truly a little Chriſtian Patience, and ſome of that Perfection talked of, would have taught you this Leſſon. And you might know this, that he that is the Light of the World, is ſet as well for the Fall as for the Riſe of many in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But you have long dwelt here, uſurping Authority to condemn thoſe, God hath juſtified. Through ſuch carnal reaſoning, (as you have brought againſt me) hath the firſt appearance of Truth, in all Ages been oppoſed by the Builders and Maſters of Aſſemblies in all Sects, who are ſo right in their own eyes, that they can hardly acknowledg Truth that comes after them to have been before them, (as <hi>John</hi> did, <hi>John</hi> 3.30.) this Self-denial being too great a thing for him to do, that ſticks in form, or that is born of a Woman; ſuch, with <hi>Rachel,</hi> cannot live except they bring forth Children in their own likeneſs. There are many innocent, meek, and tender-hearted amongſt you, that are and ſhall be willing in the day of his Power, to follow him in his Reſurrection, through the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, deſpiſing the ſhame of being caſt out of your Synagogues, and of being diſown'd of their Mother's Children, who in Patience and great Tribulations will follow the Lamb, and poſſeſs his Crown. And theſe are the true Tribe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> (or <hi>Jeſus</hi>) that are fit to make Princes in all Lands.</p>
            <p>And whereas one of you asked me, <hi>Whether I would have you one with the World, and turn Drunkards, Cheaters?</hi> &amp;c. I replied: Canſt thou not ſee a middle Path to walk in betwixt theſe two Extremes of open Prophaneneſs, and cloſe ſpiritual Wickedneſs in high places? nor put a difference between the true Chriſt that filleth all, and is the Firſt-born in every Creature, and the falſe Chriſt, that is only here or there, in that Mountain, or in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Chamber, covered over with appearing righteous before Men, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ravening, and with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> in the bitter Spirit, giving Wormwood with Gall to drink, puſhing with the ſide and ſhoulder, and piercing all thoſe innocent Ones, that can call neither you nor no Man Maſter of their Spirits, ſave God only, nor receive your Mark, nor yet the Number of your Name?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43178:5"/>And is not this the Abomination that maketh deſolate, and ſtandeth in the holy Place (the Heart) where Love and Innocency ſhould dwell? And Proſelytes thus begot, and made, tho appearing never ſo righteous, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch be not ſeven-fold more the Children of Hell than before? let the wiſe in Heart judg. Well, my Friends, when you come to underſtand how an Habitation may be built for the Devil by your Anger, Wrath, Backbiting, evil Surmiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by your hearkening to, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Men, obſerving of Days, and appointed Meetings, together with other Traditions, and outward Obſervations, which the Power of Love leads not to, but are begotten and continued, either by the Letter, or elſe Man's vain Philoſophy, or Example; in which having once loſt your Guide, <hi>viz.</hi> the pure and ſingle movings of the Lord, as by a great and ſtrong Wind ye are whirled about, and left to your own Thoughts and Imaginations, where the Lord is not felt; ſo you run again into thoſe outward Obſervations, where once his preſence was, and there are ſtruck blind, as the <hi>Aſſyrians, Egyptians, Iſraelites,</hi> &amp;c. were, and as <hi>Saul</hi> was, that ye utterly loſe the Door and Way that leads to Life. Read that can underſtand. And here [in this Spirit) is the ſilly Woman led captive, ever learning and talking of Truth, Light, and Love to Enemies, and brotherly Kindneſs, Meekneſs, Gentleneſs, and of patient bearing and ſuffering of all things, but never able to come into the things talked of, no nearer than in ſhew or in ſelf-imagination and outward appearance only. And in Truth I have been oft made to cry out amongſt you, how that I ſaw Chriſt muſt ſuffer, and that he muſt die (or diſappear) and then afterwards riſe, and enter into Glory. Which thing I now ſee you have not rightly underſtood. And if theſe my words ſeem to you as a Dream, yet why are you angry with me for my Dream's ſake? But theſe things I leave to the Judgment of the Great Day near at hand, wherein many will be ſmitten with Sickneſs, VVeakneſs, and the Sleep of Death, becauſe they diſcerned not Love to be the Lord's Body, and could not patiently wait for the Reſurrection thereof, but have ſet up other Idols in their Hearts inſtead of him; yet as for the innocent, harmleſs, merciful, meek, loving and kind hearted amongſt you, and of every Nation, ſuch ſhall obtain and inherit the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Peace, Plenty, and Reſt, which none can diſturb, but not till the laſt Enemy (or Enmity, which is the Sting of Death) be deſtroyed, and put underfoot. Thus by the Life of Love Death loſeth its Sting, the Grave its Victory, the Law its Strength, and all reſigned to the Conqueſt of Love unfeigned. Then are the Kingdoms of this VVorld become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and his Chriſt, and he alone reigneth. Go ye with all Sects, and learn what this meaneth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43178:6"/>Oft-times many amongſt you (in much contempt) have asked me, <hi>Whom I have coverted? and where the Fruit of my Miniſtry is?</hi> To whom I now anſwer, That my Work is with the Lord, having delivered up my Kingdom unto him, my ſelf can do nothing; but as Love moveth, ſo I either go or come, ſpeak or am ſilent: And I am not ſent to call the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, or to gather into Sects or Opinions; nor is it the ground of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing to have a Multitude follow me, or to flock about the outward Court, or that Devils themſelves are made ſubject; no, I know no true Happineſs, nor a Kingdom everlaſting in theſe things; neither ſee I any reaſon to prefer one Sect above another; only ſuch, whoſe Names are written in the Book of Love, and by it are gathered into the Life thereof, thoſe to me are moſt choice and precious. My Miniſtry is neither, Lo here, nor, Lo there: I am not ſo ſent to preach, but as a Light to the Gentiles, and to open Myſteries, interpret Dreams and hard Sayings, that have lain hid ever ſince the World (that lies in the Apoſtacy) began, that ſo the blind in Heart may ſee the things that belong to their Souls Peace and VVelfare, that ſo every one in all Forms may ſit under his preſent Attainment (as his proper Vine) and drink VVaters of Life from his own Ciſtern, without the leaſt ſpot or defilemenr of Enmity in their Feaſts of Charity, both with the Lord, and with one another. And who will be offended at the fooliſhneſs of this Preaching, except it be the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Fair-ſayers</hi> in every Sect, that are highly exalted in themſelves (and in others) becauſe of their Gifts both in praying and ſpeaking, and in their Zeal, earneſtneſs, and fervent working of their own Spirit, where ſits that painted and well-favoured Harlot (upon all Waters or Sects) ſpeaking as with the Tongue of Men and Angels, the Words of Truth, and of the Fame of Life and Love, but from that Principle which leadeth into the <hi>Chambers of Death,</hi> in all which things (the <hi>Good Man</hi> not being at home, nor endowing with Power from on high) great Abominations, Murders, and Adulteries are committed in Spirit and Heart, as in the matter of <hi>Peor,</hi> in the days of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lak</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> Figures of this untoward Generation, whoſe Ear being once opened, heard the words of God, and with the ſingle eye ſaw and knew the ſecret Counſel of the Moſt High, but afterwards falling into a Trance, (mark) into his own Imaginations, he then opened the double Eye (for he had two) and this ſaw Evil, and loved the Wages of Unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; yet nevertheleſs what he had once ſeen with the ſingle Eye, he could talk of (as you do) and ſo ſpeak of exceeding high and great Myſteries, (as one having all Knowledg (mark) that puffs up) ſo could ſpeak of the Seed of God, its beginning and end, and of the Light or Way through which it paſſeth, and that it ſhould be glorious, and inherit the Bleſſing, and could wiſh his laſt end in it. Mark, O <hi>Balak,</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> who are but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43178:6"/>one, from thy own Mouth and Practice is thy Condemnation. Thus Man's Spirit (the Witch of <hi>Endo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) being raiſed to its height, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the Conſciences of others, and upheld there, firſt began the Apoſtacy; and in this Spirit doth the Apoſtacy ſtill ſtand and ſubſiſt, even to this very day, in every Sect? and if any one of them could obtain their Will, they would be as great as the Pope, and make all others bow, and come in to them, elſe neither buy nor ſell, nor live in Love and Peace with any. But this bitter envying is not ſo with the God-like and true Chriſtians, ſuch bleſs, and not curſe. Nothing will be acceptable but what proceeds from the Root of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> and is the Off-ſpring of the pure Movings of Love, all elſe is but as the Offering of <hi>Cain,</hi> and as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of <hi>Eſau,</hi>) which, muſt be rejected, and cannot inherit the Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Joſeph</hi> being delivered out of Priſon, and the deep Pit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his <hi>Brethren</hi> had put him, where he paſſed through divers Trials and Temptations, both of Soul and Body; I ſay, being now riſen with Chriſt, and made Lord over that Earth which held him, can with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſpeak what he hath ſeen and heard. And conſidering how contrary to my Life, which was Peace and good Will to all, I have been acted in Strife and Contention for near theſe ſeven years, (ever ſince the difference firſt brake forth betwixt <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>J. N.</hi>) the which I call <hi>my ſtrange Work,</hi> as to Man, and to <hi>my ſelf.</hi> But the Lord, who doth in Heaven and Earth what he pleaſeth, in that day ſhewed me, that was the leaſt able (for this Work of War) of all my Brethren. Many things that began to appear, and to wax ſtrong, which were for deſtruction, and the one thing needful, <hi>viz.</hi> Love in Truth, even amongſt Brethren, much neglected; ſo, as the Lord commanded, I ſold my Coat of Peace and good Will to all, and bought a Sword, the which I girded upon my Thigh, and in the ſtrength of God's Command drew it, and therewith ſpared neither ſmall nor great; yet my chief Aim ever were againſt <hi>Agag,</hi> the fat and faireſt, the King and Head of that bitter Spirit <hi>Amalek,</hi> which would not ſuffer them to paſs peaceably through his Land whom the Light guided out of their received Traditions; and notwithſtanding their Talk of Light and Love, ſuch ſoon ſelt and found the Dragon's Power, and <hi>Herod, (viz. G, F.)</hi> with his Men of War, to ſtand in the croſs Ways, ready to cut off all the Innocent, that would not own him King, and call him Maſter, receive their Mark, and Number of their Name, againſt which Spirit the Sword of the Lord hath been ſharp, and will moſt certainly chop the ſame in pieces, as Herbs for the Pot. And though this was War indeed, yet foraſmuch as the ground and root thereof had the Command of God,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43178:7"/>and Love to Truth, ſuch Weapons are Spiritual, I ſay, it was a War in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Well, Friends, <hi>Joſeph</hi> hath been with the Lord in the Deep, and hath there ſeen his Wonders, wherefore receive theſe things kindly and friendly from his Treaſury, they may prove a ſupply to you in this Day of Famine, not of Bread, but of the Loving-kindneſs of the Lord towards one another. And be not offended at what is ſpoken, tho it tend to the throwing down of Man into the Duſt, yet if God and his Grace be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by exalted, give up Self to the Death of the Croſs. It is good to die with the Lord, tho Fleſh and Blood ſee not this. Neither be you troubled nor offended at him that declares theſe things, tho he ſeems ſometimes to appear as a Man walking on the Sea, which is rough, foaming, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> is now out of Priſon, and hath no more Conſcience of an Idol; to him no Idol is anything, neither <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Apollos,</hi> no, nor <hi>Chriſt after the Fleſh</hi> he knows no more, neither their <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> nor <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> nor any outward thing, nothing but <hi>Grace that works by Love.</hi> I have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence, nor Worſhip, nor Fear, nor Care for any thing, ſave that I worſhip the only alone true <hi>LORD GOD,</hi> who is Love; any thing acted out of that, I value not.</p>
            <p>And I clearly ſee, that ſuch a People the Lord will bring forth, as the praiſe of his new Creation, that in the quietneſs and ſtilneſs of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (which is <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder) do patiently wait for the immediate Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of Love (which is <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Cup wherein he propheſied) freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to the Will of God in all things, relying on his Grace for their only Guide, and not ſo much as lift up a Tool, or make any Noiſe or Complaint in his Work, nor (with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi>) hold up a hand of Fear or Care that it ſhould fall, or that his Will ſhould not be accompliſhed and brought to paſs in its due time and ſeaſon. No, Friends, thoſe that have hitherto attained, are not of them that look back to ſee what others will do, but have preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on to the Mark, Chriſt (the Love of God in their Hearts) his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Fulneſs, where they ſee their Souls ſaved, and have learned always to pray, <hi>Thy Will be done;</hi> whoſe Will is their Sanctification, Salvation, and Glorification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43178:7"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of ſome of <hi>R. Rich's</hi> Letters to <hi>G.F. J.C.</hi> and ſeveral others.</head>
            <p>IT is written of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that he ſet up two Calves, much like <hi>Thee, Thou,</hi> and the <hi>Hat;</hi> putting alſo a neceſſity of bowing down to them, and worſhipping, as ye do, ſaying, <hi>Theſe are thy Gods which brought thee out of</hi> Egypt, that ſo the Kingdom might not return to <hi>David,</hi> which is the <hi>Love of God.</hi> I urge not this by way of Cenſure, as raſhly judging any, even the meaneſt appearances which God draws out the Spirits of his People in, but rather to ſhew you the Idolatry of ſuch Limitations, which in theſe outward things you lay upon the boundleſs variety of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Spirit of Truth; for I have heard ſome of the chief Rulers amongſt you ſay, That if any return to the <hi>Hat</hi> again (meaning putting it off in Salutation) then all their Profeſſion is loſt; as if this, or ſuch like, were the God that redeemed them. And indeed who is there upon the Face of the whole Earth, that fears God, and worketh Righteouſneſs, if he receive not your Mark [of <hi>Thee,</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> and the <hi>Hat,</hi>] may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted or owned as a Brother amongſt you?</p>
            <p>And what is your Form of Words in <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> but a cuſtomary Singularity in Speech, another Mode of ſpeaking than is commonly uſed, which no way reſpects the Truth of what is ſpoken? Pray tell me, is not Truth (where underſtood) the Language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> in what Speech or Dialect ſoever expreſt? Or did the Diſciples of Chriſt, in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of Truth to every Man in his own Language, refuſe the Dialect either of the <hi>Medes, Perſians, Egyptians,</hi> or any other, by which they could only convey the Truth to their Underſtandings? Or is <hi>Thou</hi> more acceptable to God than <hi>You,</hi> in the declaration of Truth? I believe thoſe Words, and that Language which proceeds from the Spirit of Love, is beſt, and moſt acceptably received by them that are in the ſame Spirit.</p>
            <p>And what is there in refuſing to ſwear after that manner the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate commands, while in the mean time you will call God to witneſs to what you affirm for Truth? Is it any more than to oppoſe the Magiſtrates Form by your own? Doth not he that ſpeaks the Truth, and calleth God and Man to witneſs the ſame, ſwear by Chriſt Jeſus, the Truth and Oath of God? Doth true ſwearing conſiſt in the meer Ceremony of kiſſing the Book? or ſtandeth it not rather in calling God to record to the Truth, which we declare? And yet this manner of ſwearing is owned by <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Friends, and frequently practiſed by them, both by Word and Writing. And what is all this, but to ſwallow the Camel, and ſwear
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43178:8"/>ſubſtantially, while you ſtrain at a Gnat of ſome ſmall Ceremony, which the Magiſtrate thinks fit to enjoyn? perhaps more to obtain Credit from thoſe, who have Conſcience in ſuch a Form of Swearing, rather than to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them that know how to diſtinguiſh between the Ceremony and the Subſtance? And is not <hi>Verily, verily,</hi> an Aſſeveration, and kind of Oath, and more than <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>nay?</hi> And doth not St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay (who had Chriſt in him) that he <hi>call'd God to record?</hi> &amp;c. And is not this a great Oath? And whether you have any other thing to rule and guide you in not ſwearing, ſave the<note n="*" place="margin">Which tho it ſaith <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> yet no where forbids laving on the hand, or kiſſing the Book, the only thing you ſcruple.</note> Letter? And whether that be not more againſt you than with you? let the wiſe in Heart, who are acquainted with the Scriptures, judg in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>Thou ſayeſt, <hi>That the Goſpel of Chriſt is</hi> Yea <hi>and</hi> Amen, <hi>and that it leads not back to what it led from.</hi> I ſay, This hath been a Principle long received and taught by your Teachers, and indeed hath occaſioned much Perſecution to the Innocent amongſt you, to call your outward Obſervations and Traditions the Goſpel (or Truth); for when any have bin carried out of the way of your received Traditions into any new Appearance, how have you upon this ground riſen up againſt them, with Floods of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to devour them. To which Principle, or rather Opinion of yours, I anſwer, and ſay, That the Goſpel, Truth, or Kingdom ſtands not in any outward Obſervations; for why may not the Lord do both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth whatſoever he pleaſeth? and lead his People howſoever or whereſoever he will? How dare any find fault with him? And who ſhall ſay unto him, What doſt thou? He leadeth <hi>Abraham, Joſeph,</hi> and all <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> yea, <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth</hi> into the Wilderneſs, and doth, when he pleaſeth, turn the Courſe of his Diſpenſation, leading them back again from whence they came. Why may not God command <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſet up a Brazen Serpent, yea, and give power to it alſo, and then again withdraw his power from it, and by his Light lead <hi>Hezekiah</hi> to pull it down, and call it <hi>Nebuſhtan,</hi> which is an Idol, or nothing, altho to the very day of its diſſolution the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> burnt Incenſe to it, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, it may be, (as you alſo do) that the Lord would not relinquiſh that Appearance once eſtabliſhed by Himſelf. The Lord hath had his ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ways of appearing to his People, as in the Mount of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and at <hi>Jeruſa;em;</hi> and yet <hi>ſhe</hi> that was limited in her ſelf, was led by the Light from all this, to worſhip the Father every where, and in all places and things in the Spirit and Truth. Chriſt appeared in divers Forms, as the Scripture teſtifies, yet no other (ſave them only that ſaw him) would believe the report of him, according to their Teſtimony, but counted their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43178:8"/>Words (as <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren did his Dreams) idle Fables, as ye do, while you judg your Brethren, whom the Lord hath viſited in a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from your ſelves. What if the Lord will ſo ſtrangely appear, as to leave the <hi>Jew,</hi> and turn to the <hi>Gentile,</hi> to call them a People, that were not a People? What if God will make you that have been firſt and higheſt in Profeſſion, laſt and loweſt in the Kingdom? What if <hi>Capernaum,</hi> now exalted to the Heavens, ſhould be brought down to Hell? It will then be manifeſt, that the Almighty is not confined to either Perſons or Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances. But further, why may not the Lord lead <hi>Mordecai</hi> openly to withſtand the Pride and Oppreſſion of <hi>Haman,</hi> and at the ſame time lead <hi>Heſter</hi> in a clean contrary work to feaſt him, hereby overcoming Evil with Good? If one Perſon ſhould act theſe two parts, which ſeem ſo contrary to each other, as is Light to Darkneſs, being led thereto by the Light, whether that may not be accepted of God, tho all Men ſhould therefore condemn it? And why may not one abſtain from Meats to day, and to morrow ſee a liberty to eat? or have Conſcience of an Idol now, and anon know it to be nothing? VVere not ſome led to ſacrifice, circumciſe, and baptize, as being all beautiful, while the Power of God was in them? but <hi>that</hi> being departed, the Practiſers of thoſe things may now tell you, that they avail and profit nothing. Surely did but all Sects knowingly conſider, that in my Fathers Houſe are many Manſions, and that his Commands are exceeding broad (and various) that there are diverſities of Adminiſtrations and Operations, yet the ſame Spirit work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all, and in all: and was the Subſtance (which is the Grace appearing to all) more minded by Profeſſors, and the Form leſs; alſo were the weightier Matters of the Law, as Mercy, Juſtice, Truth, and Love, more in eſtimation than the leſſer, which only ſtand in outward Obſervations, and are but the outſide of the Diſh and Platter in all Forms, there would not be ſuch tearing one another for the Form's ſake. For in the Subſtance and weightier Matters all People of all ſorts do without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy agree, yet every one in and for the Houſe of his Imagery rends and devours his Brother, not equally faſhioned and made up in the ſame proportion of Underſtanding, as touching our outward Behaviour in the Truth's Profeſſion, by which the Image of the Heavenly is indeed ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, that the pure Love which thinks no ill (amongſt all Profeſſors of Godlineſs) is very rarely and hardly found. Theſe are indeed the bitter VVaters that cauſe the Curſe upon all Sects, Nations, Tongues, and Peoples, as at this day; this devours the Earth, and makes all deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; this profanes the Lord's own Sanctuary, and the Princes thereof, and cauſeth <hi>Jacob</hi> to be given to the Curſe, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Reproaches. For this kind of Spirit of bitter envying is indeed that City <hi>Meroz,</hi> which no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43178:9"/>way helpeth the Lord in his VVork, for it doth not beget to love. And is it not moſt juſt that that Name or Form ſhould be left for a Curſe, that deſpiſeth the Innocent for theſe outward things? but I truſt, and am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that the Lord will in his due time free the Earth from this Curſe.</p>
            <p>Thou askeſt me, <hi>How I could compare or liken thy Friends Actions to the Pope, or to them in</hi> New-England, <hi>calling them your Forefathers, ſeeing</hi> (as thou ſayeſt) <hi>thy Friends bear their Teſtimony againſt the Pope's Idolatry and Perſecution, and alſo have ſuffered Deach for a Teſtimony againſt the</hi> New-England <hi>Oppreſſion?</hi> To all which I anſwer, and ſay, That the Spirit of Perſecution is but one throughout all Generations and Forms, tho never ſo refined; for he that murders in <hi>New-England</hi> is the ſame that impriſons at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet each bear a Teſtimony againſt one anothers Forms. The ſame Spirit of Perſecution have I ſeen and obſerved amongſt thoſe which thou calleſt <hi>Friends,</hi> who for a Song of <hi>Zion,</hi> or a Shout of inward Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or any other thing that ſuites not with their Traditions or Forms, can with the ſame Spirit of Perſecution caſt out of their Synagogues, ſmite with the Fiſt of VVickedneſs, and wound with the venomed Arrow of their Reproaches, thoſe who cannot ſubmit, or join with them in their way. And this is not falſly to accuſe the Brethren, as thou chargeſt me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, for any to tell you what they have heard and ſeen amongſt you; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a juſt return of your own Money into your own Sacks, that you may meaſure your dealings with the Innocent by your own Practices; and when the Witneſs of God ariſeth amongſt you, and ſheweth you your Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wherein you have offended thoſe that have been otherwiſe acted than our ſelves, then will you know that theſe things are Truth, and the Deſolation that ſhall be in your Houſe at that day, ſhall teſtify to your Faces that a Prophet hath been amongſt you. When (mark what I ſay) it ſhall ſo come to paſs, that the ſame Wrath and Vengeance ſhall break out upon you from others, which you have heaped upon the Backs of thoſe who were juſtified in their Hearts and Ways before the Lord, then know (and you ſhall aſſuredly) that I have not ſpoken Lies unto you, or forged a falſe Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation amongſt you. What I have here charged upon ſome, I would not be underſtood to lay it upon all that have been called, and are known by the Name of <hi>Quakers.</hi> I know the Lord hath his People amongſt them; as in all Forms, both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſuch as love and fear the Lord, doing the thing which is juſt and right; and ſuch are accepted with me, as Bone of my Bone, and as my Brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi> that came of the Free-Woman, and are in that Freedom fitted to act in all Forms, as the Lord their Light ſhall lead them, that they may repleniſh the Earth. And thoſe who are come to this Freedom, <hi>viz.</hi> to give the Light its Liberty of leading, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it enlightens every Man that comes into the World in all Forms
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43178:9"/>and Appearances, the Curſe is taken away, the Enmity is departed, and the Earth become the Lord's, and his Chriſt's. Let him that can, receive it, as doth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <epigraph>
               <q>And when your Work is done, and come to an end, then ſhall the Stone from <hi>Sion</hi> you ſtumbled at, be ſet up with ſhouting, crying <hi>Grace, Grace unto it.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Zech. 4.7.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THere are divers Operations and Diſpenſations, yet all good, as having their beginning and End in God. And why therefore may not God enjoin that as an Ordinance to day, and give his power to it alſo, which to morrow he will lay aſide as uſeleſs? and by his withdrawing his Power from it, leave it no better than an Idol? Such was the Brazen Serpent; ſuch was the Temple and Tabernacle; ſuch were the Legal Offerings, the Jewiſh Ceremonies and Sacrifice; and ſuch alſo are many things at this day, (both amongſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> and other Sects) which have been Forms and Figures of good things to come, which were beautiful in their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whilſt the Preſence of God filled them, but that being withdrawn, are become dead and cold, as Idols, of no uſe. Wherefore my advice is, that all Men walk as they ſee and have received from the Lord, and none to look out at others, or to call any Man, Maſter, or Father of their Spirits, ſave God only. And if the Lord commands any to forſake Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Forms and Traditions they were brought up in, ought not all rather to obey God than Man? Conſider this, <hi>G. F.</hi> and whether to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our own Guide, and to follow thee, or any Number of People that call themſelves a Church <hi>(who take upon them to impoſe upon their Brethrens Conſciences)</hi> be not Apoſtacy? And whether this Uſurpation did not at firſt lead the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> into the Apoſtacy? And whether it will not the ſecond time lead the <hi>Quakers</hi> to apoſtatize from the true Faith once delivered to them? let the wiſe in Heart judg.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>THou accuſeſt me of being <hi>fallen, and deeply revolted from the Truth, and of being brutiſh and uncivil at your Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. What thou haſt here laid to my Charge, is not ſo much by far, as thy Generation at ſundry times hath alſo caſt on the Innocent and upright-hearted, even all manner of Evil, for bearing record to the Truth as made manifeſt in the Light, <hi>viz.</hi> by witneſſing to ſmall and great, that the Lord is my Shepherd and Teacher alone, and that I needed no Man to teach me, ſave him only; and that to thoſe who had received the Anointing, it was ſufficient to bring
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43178:10"/>to Peace and Reſt with God and Man, and to preſerve Union and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Him in all his Creation. And for this, and my rejoycing which daily I have in Chriſt Jeſus, my Lord, have I ſuffered all theſe things at your hands, and been ſet at nought by <hi>Herod,</hi> and his Men of War, even by thoſe amongſt you that would be accounted Some-body, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire preheminence, and to have Dominion over the Faith of others; and that glory in making Proſelytes, and to have a Multitude to follow them, calling you Maſters or Teachers: For by ſuch, and in this manner, have I long and oft received your Arrows, even <hi>bitter Words and Writings,</hi> which ſometimes, as I ſaw cauſe, I have returned back again into your own Boſoms; and this you call a wrangling and unruly Spirit. At preſent I have little more to ſay, than that I am reſolved to be faithful to what is committed unto me, and to declare the ſame to day, and to morrow, and alſo the third day, even till the Body be perfected, and Him ſet upon the Throne, even that Light that is in true Love, whoſe right it is to reign, (which thing tell <hi>Herod,</hi> that <hi>Fox,</hi> your King;) ſo that all may have Peace and Reſt in Him, who is only worthy of Praiſe, Honour, and Glory alone, even ſo ſaith my Spirit, <hi>Amen.</hi> I might have ſaid much more (in return to thine) but that I ſee and know that Words and Declarations, tho never ſo true, unleſs the Life it ſelf ſpeak them, and go along with them, have but little ſtrength. And I could alſo tell thee, that to forſake your Form yea, and to ſpeak againſt it too, were not to forſake Truth, as thou chargeſt. And is it not ſtrange that you ſhould ſo complain of my diſturbing your Meetings, in a Song, or few words of Truth, when as your ſelves have gone to others aſſembled, even with railing Accuſations, calling them, <hi>Dumb Dogs, Liars, Hirelings, Baal's Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. yet cannot bear with ſuch as come to admoniſh you?</p>
            <p>O that the time were come, that thoſe who deſired Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, would give it to others! I know you cannot believe the Truth when told you, nor ceaſe from reproaching, judging and condemning it; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will you let the Innocent go free, to ſerve the Lord according as their Light ſhall lead them, till the Judgments you have pronounced againſt the Innocent fall upon your own Heads. For I know that the Lord hath poured out upon you a deep Spirit of Slumber, which hath ſo blinded your Eyes, and hardened your Hearts, that in ſeeing you ſhould not ſee, neither perceive the Truth in things that differ. And there is yet a Treaſure, a Diſpenſation of Grace, where you have as yet (by reaſon of your Self-exaltation, and bitter Spirit) ſeen but little into, the which ſome have ſeen, felt, and handled. To this you muſt all ſtoop and bow, tho never ſo high, before you find Peace and Reſt to your Souls, or be free from vain Contention and Strife.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:43178:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>R. R.</hi> to<hi> M. B.</hi> and other <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis I have to ſay unto thee, or rather to <hi>G. F.</hi> who hath begot many of you into his Image, That you no longer tempt any of the innocent Lambs of Chriſt to withdraw from the leading and teaching of the Unction of God, which is Chriſt, to follow the Letter, or your Teachings or Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, wherein you muſt and ſhall periſh in the dark Wilderneſs of your own Imaginations: for the Lord hath ſworn in his Wrath, that you who call your ſelves, <hi>Good old Friends,</hi> and the <hi>Iſrael of God,</hi> who have ſo falſly accuſed, condemned, and bitterly perſecuted your innocent Brethren, (for thoſe things the Lord hath and doth juſtify) ſhall never inhabit the good Land.</p>
            <p>I know <hi>G. F.</hi> is raiſed of God for this very end, to try, refine, and purify many, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was; and tho many fall in the Trial under his Power, yet many will be delivered into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>I likewiſe ſee, that daily more and more will fall off from that Body; and that ſome that ſeparate from them, will with <hi>Daniel</hi> ſtand in their Lot, and follow the Lord in the Spirit of the Lamb more fully than they have done; whilſt they that oppoſe, ſhall ſtand with <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, turned into a Pillar of Salt, continuing their preaching up Truth in Words without Power, whilſt others baptize with the Holy-Ghoſt and with Fire.</p>
            <p>Thou writeſt of my <hi>going to the Steeple-houſe:</hi> To which I anſwer, Bleſſed are thoſe that have Reſt, Peace, and Satisfaction in themſelves! for they that look forth, are like to find but little in this the day of God's ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Candles, wherein he will ſtain the Pride and Glory of all Fleſh.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>R. R.</hi> in Anſwer to ſome Friends, not <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu judg me to be a <hi>Ranter,</hi> and to hold their Principles. I can truly ſay, I have been but little acquainted with that People, or with their Principles.</p>
            <p>I would not be thought to be an Advocate for the looſe and licentious Practices of any ſort of People, much leſs for Them, who (from the itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ☜ Notions of Liberty) have run without their Guide into the exceſs of all Riot and Prophaneneſs, who while they greedily catch at the Bait, are caught with the Hook, till a Dart ſtrike through their Liver, and they are led with the Fool to the Correction of the Stocks, and there plagued with their own Iniquities.</p>
            <p>I deſire this may be ſhewn to Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> as to all others who ſeem to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at my Love to this dark <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> this mad ranting Crew.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43178:11"/>THe time is coming, and now is, that we ſhall not know and own each other, as we are of one Sect or outward way, but as the Grace and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of God appears in each other, the Love of God ſhed abroad in our Hearts; and where this is witneſſed, thither will the Upright reſort and gather.</p>
            <p>If you ſee any dividing among the Religious Parties, take you notice of that. I know every one muſt divide, till all unite in the Word in the Heart.</p>
            <p>My Love flows to all that in uprightneſs of Heart ſerve the Lord in any Form. For as all Forms are alike to me, ſo is the Subſtance, the Power of Godlineſs alſo; and altho Uprightneſs God accepted in all Forms, and ſuffered all Sects to walk in them, yet now calleth all Men to reject the evil in each Form, and to wait on Him to be their Teacher from henceforth and for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. N.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> tho dead, yet ſpeak, who declared they were to ceaſe from words even of Truth, ſpoken from the comprehending part of Man's Underſtanding, and from [thus] ſpeaking in ſet Meetings, and ſo to give way for a greater Glory, <hi>viz.</hi> the Spirit's teaching, leading, and ſpeaking in the Saints.</p>
            <p>Alſo they declared, that they had received greater Wounds from the Houſe of their Friends, than from the Houſe of their Enemies.</p>
            <p>And I can aſſure you, they who meddle with the <hi>Quakers</hi> had need be fenced within and without, with the whole Armor of God; Truth, and love to Righteouſneſs, (<hi>David</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Sling and Stone) and enabled to uſe both hands, the left as well as the right, the Wiſdom of the Serpent, as the Innocency of the Dove.</p>
            <p>And truly till the Spirit of Love and Reconciliation be brought forth, wherewith every Chriſtian ſhall willingly leave each other to the guidance of God's holy Spirit of Grace (in that Form or Way they are perſuaded to walk in) the Strife which is occaſioned by outward Traditional Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations will never ceaſe.</p>
            <p>And I have this further to declare to all the World, to <hi>Jew, Gontile, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> (tho I know it will be an Offence and Stone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to <hi>G. F.</hi> and all Maſters of Aſſemblies in every Sect, who preſcribe, impoſe, and would have Dominion over the Faith of others) that the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God (who wills not the death of any Sinner) hath ſent his dear Son <hi>Emanuel,</hi> his Light and Spirit of Grace into the World, his everlaſting Covenant, a Divine Law writ in every Man's Heart, that whoſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in Him, and followeth Him, ſhall have Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>And this Divine Law, and Word in the Heart, is the <hi>Enſign</hi> to gather together all things into Himſelf, and to preſent every Man perfect in God, being thereby ſanctified, juſtified, and ſaved from their Sins. To which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43178:11"/>Word in the Heart, God's Preacher, his Law, and Covenant of Grace to all the World, do I recommend all Sects and Opinions, as the only Rule of their Souls Progreſs into everlaſting Peace and Reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>G. H.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 25. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>LAſt ſeventh day I was at the <hi>Bridge Town,</hi> viſiting thoſe Friends in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; as I parted from them, I ſpake to <hi>H. Fell,</hi> to conſider wherein I might be ſerviceable to them, in ſupplying any of their Wants; and told him, I was very willing in ſome ſmall proportion to bear a part in their Sufferings: and therefore deſire thee to ſupply them with what may be needful, to the value of 2000 or 3000 Pound of Sugar. For as I then told <hi>H. F.</hi> altho I have ſome difference with them as to their Form and Practice, yet notwithſtanding, in the Principle of Love and Light I am one with them, yea, and all Men, in ſuffering for the Teſtimony of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God, altho that thing for which they ſuffer (in my Light) be rendred as a meer Idol, which indeed is nothing. For I well know, and have long ſeen, that Mens Conſciences are variouſly guided; ſome by the Spirit of Love, under whoſe Leadings is the trueſt and moſt perfect Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; others by the Law or Letter, where (with the outward <hi>Jew</hi>) they are held in Bondage to Meats, Drinks, ſet-Days of Meetings, and divers Forms, and other carnal Ordinances. Others may be led barely by the Traditions of their Fathers, in and after the Laws and Cuſtoms of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or by the Authority of that Church or Fellowſhip under which they have been educated, and herein may be zealouſly devoted to thoſe Rudiments which in themſelves are poor and beggarly, nay, ſuch as the Reaſon of Man (if not captivated) would abhor to be brought under. But in and amongſt all theſe, he that fears God, and doth the thing that is juſt and right to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Man, is accepted with Him, and is one with whom I am in perfect Union. And if any, becauſe he thinks himſelf wiſer and higher than ſuch an one, preſume to be his Judg or Law-giver, this is that which exalteth it ſelf above all that is called God, and diſhonoureth Chriſt his Head, that true Light, wherewith every one is enlightned that comes into the World. And indeed if we will not allow the Light (as it is received) to lead every one, we ſhall never be free from ſmiting our Fellow-ſervants, and ſlaying that innocent and juſt one in each other, whom the Lord hath ſet up as a Ruler over the Nations, and for an Enſign of Light in every Man's Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Thus indeed and in truth I am for the free Leadings of the Light in all that profeſs the ſame, but wherein their Practice falls ſhort of this their Profeſſion, I do confeſs I ſtand therein at a diſtance from them. For I allow not that any creep into Houſes, (to wit, the Conciences of others,) and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there; for this is to lead captive ſilly Women, or to force upon the weak
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43178:12"/>Underſtanding a Conformity to thoſe things which the Light of Love never moved to, but is rather acted from a Principle of Fear, leſt they ſhould be call out of the Synagogue by thoſe who uſurp Authority, and are called by them Maſters. The conſideration of the freeneſs of thy Mind occaſioned me to impart to thee a taſte of my Underſtanding in theſe things, which thou mayeſt either accept or refuſe, as the Light in thee ſhall make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. I am a Friend to thee, and the whole Creation of God, in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Light, which is Love unfeigned.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> Governor of the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu were pleaſed to expreſs a tender regard to the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> alſo to require my advice how beſt they might be preſerved as Subjects, with equal regard to Juſtice, and the Safety of this Place. Yeſterday I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted one of thoſe People with your Lordſhip's care of them, and after put ſeveral Queſtions to him touching their Freedom; alſo urged the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a <hi>Militia</hi> to defend and preſerve from thoſe that came to rob and to ſteal. After many Words <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> I find them ſetled in this, <hi>viz.</hi> That Wars proceed (as St. <hi>James, chap.</hi> 4.1. ſaith) from Mens Luſts, the which they would not help to uphold and maintain; that they were to love their Enemies, and to have Peace with all Men. In fine, my Lord, I perceive it is matter of Conſcience with them, not to uſe a carnal Sword in their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and do believe that ſome of them will ſooner loſe their Eſtates and Lives than ſin againſt their Conſciences. But to anſwer your Lordſhip's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, for advice how this People may be preſerv'd in this Iſland, with equal regard to Juſtice, and the Safety of this Place; My humble advice is, That ſeeing for Conſcience ſake many of them cannot make uſe of carnal Weapons, your Lordſhip would nevertheleſs protect them, they paying for their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection what is juſt and equal, that the State and Common-weal be not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, but rather bettered and advanced by them. This way the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> took with the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who held the Scriptures to be their Rule, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſwear, nor yet to fight. Firſt; As to ſwearing, the Magiſtrate accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated them, by taking their Teſtimony with only declaring the Truth as in God's Preſence, with Hands lifted up, as in token thereof; and this was ſufficient without further Teſtimony or Words; and theſe kind of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (they being conſcientious) have been found the beſt for diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the Truth. And as to the maintaining of Wars, and other Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies of State, thoſe People paying Scot and Lot as their Neighbours, have quiet and peaceable Protection. And if all that are able in this Iſland muſt of neceſſity bear Arms to defend the ſame, and <hi>Quakers</hi> for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43178:12"/>ſake cannot; if the Magiſtrate cauſe them to be taxed for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, ſo much, and no more than will find Horſe and Foot in their room, they paying alſo the juſt Charge and Trouble of gathering in the ſame, I cannot ſee but ſuch a Courſe would not only preſerve them, but alſo anſwer all juſt ends of Government. All which I humbly preſume, under your Lordſhip's Favour and Command, to preſent unto your Honour's View and Conſideration.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>Theſe two foregoing Letters ſhew the Tenderneſs of his Spirit towards all, even to thoſe that were the moſt bitter againſt him.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Abſtracts of ſome Letters to the Lady <hi>F. V.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Year 1654 I became a <hi>Quaker,</hi> which Diſpenſation of <hi>John</hi> I was truly Baptiz'd into, Repentance and amendment of Life; which blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out all my former Sins, and for two years time was (in the ſtrength of that Baptiſm) carried with delight, both to do and to ſuffer, even above and beyond my equals; all which time I lived after the Mode of that Sect; a ſevere ſtrict life, a Phariſee of the Phariſees; till in the year 1656, when my dear Brother <hi>J. N.</hi> ſuffer'd for confeſſing to Chriſt in the Saints; my love to that Teſtimony made me willing to ſtand by him in his Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to bear his Croſs: for which Teſtimony the World (the Powers of darkneſs then ruling) my Kindred, and my Brethren the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſold me into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> by their many falſe reports; yet there the Lord my God appeared to me, and finding me in my Innocency wherewith he had clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed me, hath ever fince become my exceeding great Reward.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Nov.</hi> 30. 1678.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>BY what I have formerly and now ſent for <hi>England,</hi> you may ſee how I have bin acted for many years. Lately I have heard a Voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſaying, <hi>Turn thy Sword into Plowſhares and into Pruning Hooks; ſtay at home, Dreſs and keep clean the Garden of</hi> Eden <hi>[thine own Heart] that no root of bitterneſs ſpring up there.</hi> I alſo now begin to feel an inclination to write out fair that which long ſince I have prepared, and to preſent each of the ſeven Churches of Chriſtendom, with an Epiſtle I formerly intended them. Then will many come to ſee beyond the Letter of that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Viz.</hi> the Gift of <hi>210</hi>l. to the <hi>7</hi> Churches <hi>An. 1666.</hi>
               </note> Action, and not the ſound of Words only, nor from <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> but from <hi>Sion,</hi> where it is written, <hi>In the Mount of the Lord it ſhall be ſeen,</hi> and heard by all that have an Ear to hear what the Spirit ſaith; at whoſe Voice of Love our Friend <hi>Lazarus</hi> will awake, and riſe out of his ſleep.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43178:13"/>In truth I thought the Epiſtles promiſed, would ſoon have followed my Gift, but in ſhort time after I came to ſee, that the day was not for Unity and Amity, but for biting and devouring one another; ſo that inſtead of raiſing our Brother <hi>Lazarus,</hi> we had our hands every one againſt his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, two againſt three, and three againſt two; which work tended to the Crucifying of the Lord of Life afreſh: but I hope the day is dawning, that after Ages [or next Diſpenſation] will ſpeak more reverently of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Amity. I have bin made (contrary to my Nature) a Man of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and ſtrife to all the World, one that at the command of the Lord hath ſold my Coat (made of Love and Good-will to all) and bought a Sword, with which I have fought a long and tedious Battel (of about ten years ſtanding) againſt all Profeſſors of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of Chriſt; which War (I believe) will go on throughout the whole World, to the deſtruction of all Idols in all Religions, and to the ſetting up of Chriſt Jeſus (God's Word in the Heart, his Prieſt and Prophet) King over all the Earth. <hi>His Fan is in his hand, and he will throughly purge his Floor,</hi> even all the Children of Light, that they may offer to the Lord, in a clean Veſſel (of His own) an Offering in Righteouſneſs: Wherefore be ye clean [pure Virgins] that bring forth the Birth of God, and bear the Veſſels of the Lord. Thus all that are baptized into this one Spirit of Love to Truth and Righteouſneſs, ſtand as Saviours on Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> (with the Trump of God in their Hearts) to judg and ſave the Mount of <hi>Eſau,</hi> not in a wrathful bitter Spirit, but in the ſame loving-kindneſs, wherewith God hath judged and ſaved us; for ſo will the Kingdoms of this World become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall and muſt reign for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>I confeſs formerly (for a long time) I have had Conſcience of an Idol, and contended only for one ſort of People; but now an Idol to me is nothing, and my preſent ſtate is, to own that which is of God in any ſort of Men, and to become all things to that of God in all Men (that is not of Sin) that ſo I may reach, ſave, and unite (in the Love of God) all Men to each other in all Religions, which Love ſhed abroad in our Hearts is God's Salvation to all Men, even to the ends of the Earth.</p>
            <p>I have here ſent my Epiſtle to the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> that by this you may ſee the Patern of the reſt, which Patern I received ſome years ſince from the Mountain of God's Love, not from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> but from Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> the Habitation of the Bleſſed, the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who is Father and Mother, Brother and Siſter of all God's Children, who are regenerate, and born again of the Seed and Spirit of Grace, God's Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. At the revelation of which, when I ſaw and conſidered the end of the Lord in that my ſaluting of the ſeven Churches, my Heart did leap and skip within me, like to a Roe or young Hart upon the Mountain of Spices.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43178:13"/>I ſay, in this Mountain of God's Love (the ſanctified Heart) ſtands the Saviour, Chriſt, our Lord, (the Spirit of the Father) who ſaves his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their Sins, the which ſanctifies and redeems them from all Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Who is, who was, and who is to come, one and the ſame through all Generations, from everlaſting to everlaſting.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1677.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>And now I ſhall ſettle to write out fair what I have prepared for the remaining ſeven Churches. That already ſent, I think, hath no contention or ſtrife in it; if you ſee any thing of that Nature, I pray take it out of the way. My Mind is directed in this Teſtimony of the univerſal Love of God to the World, to receive and treaſure up (as in <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Store-houſes) all that which is of God in every Religion, and to hand it forth in this time of Famine (of Love to God and our Neighbour) which is ſeen to break in (as an overflowing Scourge) over all Chriſtendom, not only in <hi>Egypt,</hi> amongſt the Prophane, but amongſt Profeſſors of all ſorts, who account themſelves the Sons of <hi>Jacob:</hi> And what I ſee to be falſe and reprobate Silver, (the Inventions, Traditions, and Impoſitions of Men) to return that back again, as their own Money, in their own Sacks. And in ſo doing I hope none will be offended thereat.</p>
            <p>You need not be careful or ſollicitous in publiſhing what I ſend, only when you feel your Mind in frame, (whether as in a Cloud, or Pillar of Fire) fitting and preparing to ſuch an end, gently follow after it, as it lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; for they that are come into the Faith of God's Elect, the ſecond Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, do not make haſte, but are entred into their Reſt, even into God's everlaſting Sabbath of Reſt, where (in the new Covenant of Grace) in Matters Spiritual, they ceaſe from their own Works, (from labouring and toiling in the firſt Covenant of Works,) as He did from His.</p>
            <p>The Days approaching are evil to all Worſhippers in the outward Court, <hi>Lo here,</hi> and <hi>Lo there,</hi> where the Potſherds of the Earth will daſh one againſt another, and bring all into Confuſion. This is the portion of the Ungodly, that have not the Birth of God in them. In this time of Trouble will God build his Church and Temple, the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in the ſanctified Hearts of his People, wherein he will place his Name for ever. And as for thoſe that worſhip God in the Spirit of Truth, ſuch he will ſave and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve as his Jewels in the hollow of his hand. Wherefore to your Tents O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> you that are circumciſed in Heart (and Ears) enter ye into your Maſter's Joy, the Love of God ſhed abroad in your Hearts, the Ark and Tabernacle which God (not Man) hath pitched in all the Sanctified, and be therein at Peace with that of God in all his Creation. So will you come to the everlaſting Sabbath of Reſt, which God hath prepared for all that love him, and wait for his Appearance.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1678.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43178:14"/>
            <head>More Abſtracts of Letters to particular Friends.</head>
            <p>I Received yours, which I accepted as an ample Teſtimony of your endeared Union with the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> of our Souls, in which I greatly rejoice to meet you one in the footſteps of his Companions, enquiring where He maketh his Flocks to reſt at Noon, as not willing to ſhade your ſelf under any falſe Reſt or Security, but waiting in the Patience and Faith of the Saints, till his Power of Grace from on high more abundantly ſhines forth, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadows the whole Earth with the Glory of his <hi>Immanuel.</hi> This Spirit of Love is the Tree of Life, whoſe Leaves are for the healing of the Nations, and under the infinite ſpreading Branches thereof, we may all of every Nation, Sect, or People, ſit down together (the Wolf with the Lamb) in ſafety and peace. In the humble expectation and patient waiting of my Spirit, for the full manifeſtation of this all-ſaving Grace, I dearly ſalute you, together with all Saints; in whoſe Bodies, as in the Clouds, I ſee the Lord coming to reconcile all things to Himſelf, through the death of Sin, by nailing the Enmity to his Croſs, which is the Power of Love, and by that Life ſwallow up Death into Victory. As for my ſelf, it hath pleaſed the Lord to lead me through various Changes and Operations, ſhewing me the Wonders of his Power. Many years ſince I heard a Voice in the Wilderneſs, preaching Repentance for the Remiſſion of Sins, and to prepare a Way for the Lord, by putting off the Old Man, with his deeds; under which Diſpenſation of the <hi>Quakers</hi> (as that of <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>John</hi>) I was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in that Cloud, and there abode, till Judgment was brought forth into Victory. Afterwards being called up higher, by receiving a double meaſure of the Spirit, ſate down in Heavenly Places with Chriſt Jeſus, whence I heard a Voice ſaying, In whomſoever I ſaw the Spirit deſcending like a Dove, and abiding, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Spirit of Meekneſs, of Innocency, and of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Charity.) that this was and is the Son of God, in whom He is always well pleaſed. And Him (not my ſelf) I preach for Salvation to the ends of the Earth; Him who was before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, and is now and for ever the ſame, throughout all Generations. From which root of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Salutation of me <hi>R. R.</hi> to the ſeven Churches of Chriſtendom, that all of every Form or Sect of People in the World might (ceaſe from Man, and all other Idols) look up unto Him, and be ſaved. I ſee the Multitude of all S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts ſtanding at this day with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount, each under their proper Attainments, contending with one another, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning all others (both Perſons and Things) that ſuit not with their Laws, and legal Diſcoveries of Truth; every one in their Tribes highly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43178:14"/>pretending to the Glory of God, but in truth only tending to crucify the Son of God afreſh, and put him to open ſhame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>July</hi> 2. 1670.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To another Friend.</head>
            <p>WHerefore, ye Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion,</hi> ye Inhabitants of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> blow ye the Trumpet of God; ſay ye, The Lord reigneth; make ye a joyful Noiſe, that the whole World, and all therein, may ring and ſing forth his Praiſe; whoſe Name, Worſhip, and Nature, is one and the ſame, moſt excellent; yea, whoſe Name is alſo Truth in the inward parts, the Word in the Heart, that whoſoever walketh in the Truth and Light manifeſted in every Conſcience (of all or any Religion) ſhall be ſaved.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To other Friends.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Hearts,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Lately ſaw you ſent forth, as Sheep amongſt Wolves; therefore be ye as wiſe as Serpents, and as innocent as the Dove: In the Power that ſends you forth, ſtand, and for it wait; then as any thing is to be done, it will ariſe. And when you are before thoſe that would rule over your Conſcience, take no thought, neither be at all careful what you ſhall ſpeak, for it ſhall be given you at that inſtant. Thus will you come to witneſs the Lilly, which is more glorious than <hi>Solomon.</hi> Behold! I go before you into <hi>Galilee</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whither our Lord (the Power) is gone to gather all things into Himſelf; for out of <hi>Egypt</hi> will he bring his Son. But wait you at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (the Mother of us all) for the Power (which is the Father that begat us of his own good will and pleaſure) into which, and by which, the gathering of the People will be and not by Words or Sounds, neither into Sects or Opinions; but whoſoever is Servant to the Power, will be accepted, of what Nation, Kindred, or People ſoever he be. This is a true and faithful Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; bleſſed is he that can receive it; ſuch an one comes to ceaſe from his own Labours, and hath reſt and peace in God, to which I commend you, and in it abide; Your Brother,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Theſe are the Days of Vengeance, wherein none can live in Peace, that cannot paſs by an Injury, love their Enemies, and reward Evil with Good.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>The END.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 11. lin. 30. for <hi>were,</hi> read <hi>was.</hi> P. 16. l. 25. for <hi>our,</hi> read <hi>your.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
